大 卫·爱 登 堡
野  外  探  险  60  年
在我摄制自然纪录片的生涯之中
In a lifetime of natural history filmmaking
出品人     大卫·爱登堡
我见过许多奇异的动物
I've seen many odd animals,
这其中却少有像婆罗洲长鼻猴
but few odder than these
这样奇特的
proboscis monkeys in Borneo.
我第一次看见它们是五十年前了
I first saw them 50 years ago.
有天晚上我们撞大运了
'Late one evening, we had a great stroke of luck.'
一群奇异的长鼻猴
'For a troupe of the extraordinary long nosed proboscis monkey
跳下树丛到河岸边觅食
'had come down to the river bank to feed.'
当我开始拍摄这些生物时发现
'When I started filming such creatures,
其实要把这些至今为止
'it was quite easy to show
只有强悍的探险者才见过的生物
viewers animals that hitherto had only
展现给普通观众还是挺简单的一件事
'been seen in the wild by intrepid explorers.'
随着时间推移
'As the years passed,
经过不断尝试后  我们终于拍到了一些比较好的镜头
one way and another, we got better 'and better shots
在此期间 我有些毕生难忘的的际遇
and in the process, I had some memorable encounters.'
嘣
Boo!
这动物很聪明
This is a very intelligent animal.
此刻三文鱼是它们的首选猎物
And top of the menu right now is salmon.
我想这已经不言自明了
I think that was pretty clear!
能够生活在
I've been lucky enough to live through
可以说是自然纪录片制作的黄金时代
what might be considered the golden age
我非常幸运
of natural history filmmaking.
几乎每年我们都能找到不同的方法
Almost every year it seemed we found some new way
来揭示自然世界的新奥秘
of revealing new things about the natural world.
20世纪50年代时
'In the 1950s,
地球上多数野生生物尚未被拍摄记录
much of the wildlife of the planet was still unfilmed,
甚至无人知晓
even unknown.
在之后的60年里
'And in the following 60 years,
技术革新的成功使得我们
'a succession of technical innovations enabled us
能愈发细致地揭示自然世界
to reveal more and more of the natural world in increasing detail.'
镜   海   浮   生
这是我在1934年看过的第一部自然纪录片
This is the first natural history film I ever saw -
当时我八岁
in 1934, when I was eight.
那时我觉得这太神奇了
And I thought it was wonderful.
女士们 先生们
Ladies and gentlemen.
我将即刻带你们脱离苦难
Let me put you out of your misery at once.
尽管我正在邀请你们随我踏上这段旅程
You're not going to see me for long,
但你们不会一直看得到我
although I am inviting you to come on this trip with me,
我们只会偶尔相见
you will only see me occasionally.
戴着遮阳帽的这位是契尔瑞·凯尔顿
The man in the pith helmet is Cherry Kearton,
摄制野生动物生活纪录片的先驱之一
one of the first people to try and capture the lives of wild animals on film.
这个岛上有五百万只企鹅
There are five million penguins on this island,
它们叫做非洲企鹅 (因为它们的叫声象驴子，也被称作公驴企鹅)
which are called the jackass penguins.
[因为它们的叫声象驴叫 也被称作公驴企鹅]
我对动物一向善良友好
I'm always polite to animals,
既然我打算同这群企鹅一起呆上几个月
and as I intend to stay with the penguins for several months,
我就得用我最自然友好的礼节
I am naturally adopting my most friendly manner.
凯尔顿周游世界
Kearton travelled around the world
拍摄那些从未被拍摄过的动物
filming wild animals that had never been filmed before.
他的做法很难说是科学的
His approach was hardly scientific,
但无疑相当有趣
but nonetheless he was very entertaining.
它的姐姐 一个典型的摩登女郎
His sister, a typical flapper,
不满于普通的交配  想以夸张的方式做爱
not content with being one of the fair sex, wants to join the air sex
却这边被拒绝 那边被嫌弃
But resigns herself to just a flip here, a flap there,
里外不是人
and a flop in between.
尽管此纪录片瑕疵明显
For all its obvious flaws,
但它仍唤起我儿时的幻想
his films captured my childish imagination
使我梦想去远方拍摄野生动物
and made me dream of travelling to far-off places to film wild animals.
这是契尔瑞·凯尔顿使用过的重要摄像机之一
And this is one of the very cameras Cherry Kearton used.
它装在一个木盒里
It's enclosed in a wooden box.
人工驱动  使用35毫米胶卷
It was driven by hand and used 35mm film.
差不多这么宽
This distance across.
几年后  这种机器的升级版让人惊讶
Within a few years, it was superseded by improved models like this one,
它有了金属盒子  并且使用发条驱动
which had a metal box and it worked by clockwork
它还有了多式镜头
and it had a variety of lenses.
但它仍使用笨重的35毫米胶卷
But it still used hefty 35mm film.
值得高兴的是  还有更小型号的相机可供使用
Happily however, there were smaller versions available.
像这样的
A camera like this.
使用16毫米胶卷
This used 16mm film
这差不多是35毫米胶卷的一半大小
which was only half the size
依然是发条驱动
and it was powered by clockwork.
不幸的是 BBC节目组认为这种相机过于外行
But unfortunately the BBC thought cameras like this were unprofessional.
于是关于我能否能选择此类相机的争议很大
And there was a huge row as to whether or not I could be allowed to take it.
不过最后我还是选了
But in the end I did,
并且带着它一起开始了旅程
and it was with this I set off
漫步于丛林之中
to ramble around the jungles
找寻那些仍未拍摄过的动物
of the world looking for unfilmed animals.
在伦敦动物园帮助下
My first natural history series, Zoo Quest,
我的第一部自然系列纪录片 探寻动物园
recorded the progress of animal collecting
收集并记录了动物的成长过程
expeditions arranged with the London Zoo
并将之带上荧屏
and brought to the screen,
一些从未在电视或影院里
places and animals that had
出现过的地点和动物
never before been seen on television,
进入了人们视线
or in the cinema, come to that.
曾经有人说世界上最大的蜥蜴
One targeted the largest lizard in the world which
生活在印度尼西亚的科摩多岛
lived on the small Indonesian island of Komodo.
几乎没人听说过它们
Few people had heard of it
甚至印尼人都不确定那个岛在哪
and Indonesia no-one seemed sure where the island was.
最终 我们和一个自称见过该岛的渔夫
Eventually, we set off with a fisherman
一起出发了
who said that he did,
入海后几天 我心中起了疑虑
but after a couple of days at sea, I had my doubts.
我对船长说 你曾经是去过科摩多岛 对吧
I said to the captain, "You have been to Komodo before, haven't you?"
然后他说 Baloom
And he said, "Baloom."
我并不知道Baloom是什么意思
And I didn't know what baloom meant.
所以我不得不回去查了查印尼语词典
So I had to go and find my Indonesian dictionary and looked it up
Bloom意思是 不曾
and it said, "Not yet."
所以很明显 他并不认路
So, it was clear he didn't know the way.
海上漂行一周
After a week at sea
和许多珊瑚礁与漩涡亲密接触过后
and having survived encounters with coral reefs and whirlpools,
我们到达了我觉得该是科摩多岛的地方
we arrived at what I thought must be Komodo.
我记得我们涉水渡过一个礁湖
And I remember wading ashore across a coral lagoon
找到了一个很小的村庄
and finding a tiny little village and saying,
并询问  请问这里是科摩多岛么
"Excuse me, is this Komodo?"
然后他们说 科摩多 所以我们走对了路
And they, "Komodo". So it was OK.
当地人推荐我们用死羊当饵
The locals recommended we should use a dead goat as bait.
就同我在行程日记里记录的一样
Once in the bush we began to build a trap
我们立刻开始 用从附近搜罗来的东西
using materials gathered from nearby,
开始搭造陷阱
as I recorded in my journal.
这就是那个捕巨蜥的陷阱 里面有个小诱饵
This was the dragon trap with a little bait in there.
当巨蜥走到里面 踩到这上面时
When the dragon, if he went in the front end, trod on there,
就会释放最里面连接着绳子的环
it pulled it down which then pulled the ring down which released the rod,
绳子被底部的石块往下拉
which then pulled down, because of the lump of rock on the bottom.
就 喀嗒一声 陷阱就关上了
So, clunk, down it would go.
现在我们只需要等
And now, all we had to do was to wait.
草丛中有声响 巨蜥出现了
There was a rustle in the bush and there was the dragon.
我们第一次亲眼目睹这种巨大的怪物
Our first sight of this magnificent monster.
让我惊讶的是 我们正盯着陷阱时
To my surprise, we were looking at the trap
我背后却有声响
and I heard a noise behind me.
我回过头 就看见了巨蜥
I turned round and there was the dragon.
这就是在那个特殊时刻照的
That was taken at that particular moment.
它大概就在几码以外
Looking at me straight in the eye
直勾勾的盯着我眼睛看
from only about a couple of yards away.
我们对视了一会
We looked at each other
我想 至少我得拍张你的照片
and I thought, at least I might take your photograph.
所以就拍了这一张它的照片
So that was the photograph I took of him.
然后它似乎很疲劳地站起来
Then, he rather wearily heaved himself up
在我们身边转了两圈
and strolled round us
然后向干涸河床里我们设置陷阱走去
and went down into the dry riverbed where we'd made the trap.
然后门就关上了
And down came the door.
我们匆忙在门外堆起石头
Hastily we piled boulders on the door
所以它就开不了门
so he couldn't lift it up.
我们抓住了它
We'd got him.
早期的影片在今天而言似乎稀松平常
Those early films seem pretty ordinarily these days,
但是它们仍然广受欢迎
but they were nonetheless popular
因为那时无论我们拍了什么
because whatever we showed
都能给大多数观众们耳目一新的感觉
was new to most of our viewers.
所以在1950年代
So, in the 1950s
我们带着这样的相机走遍世界各地
we were taking cameras like this all over the world.
后来 有个奥地利生物学家兼电影制片人
And then, an Austrian biologist and filmmaker
尝试把相机带下水去
decided to try and take it under water.
他叫汉斯·哈斯
His name was Hans Hass,
为了做到这一点  他改进了自己特制的防水罩
and he developed his own special housing to do that.
汉斯和他的妻子洛特
Hans and his wife Lotte
是最早把奇妙的海底生物带到荧屏的人
were the first to bring the wonders of life under the sea to television.
因为当时很少有人有潜水经验
And their programs were all the more sensational
他们摄制的内容可以说空前轰动
because few people at that time had scuba dived.
当心 下面有鲨鱼
Take care, down there are sharks.
我们紧贴在珊瑚礁的边缘
We are right on the reef's edge.
在1950年代 鲨鱼名声狼藉
In the '50s, sharks had a terrible reputation.
它们是海洋杀手
They were the killers of the sea.
所有下水的人 遇到鲨鱼就等于遇到了死神
Anybody in water alongside a shark was clearly courting certain death.
而汉斯和洛特与鲨鱼们共游
Here were Hans and Lotte swimming alongside them.
举国震惊
The nation was astounded.
影片的播出动摇了人们的价值观
The sequence certainly had shock value,
或许这也是
but perhaps it was also
改变人们对鲨鱼看法的第一步
the first step in changing our perceptions of sharks.
那时所有电视节目一样 都是黑白的
And like all television, it was still shown in black and white.
所以在整个探索动物园系列节目里
So,during the Zoo Quest series
我需要用言语来描述动物的颜色
I had to describe an animal's colour in words.
这是世界上所有变色龙中
This one was among the most brilliantly coloured
色彩最鲜艳的一只
of all chameleons in the world.
它的眼球很亮 铁锈红
His eyeballs are bright, rust-red
身体和腿部有条形的鲜绿色疙瘩
and his body and legs striped and blotched with a vivid green.
但是电视技术飞速发展
But, television was changing fast.
1960年代 BBC有了第二个电视网络
In the 1960s, the BBC was given a second television network
它以更高的科学技术为平台
operating on a higher technical standard with the specific
引入了彩色电视
job of introducing colour television.
1965年 我在伦敦电视中心的
And in 1965, I was put in charge of it with an office
办公室里负责接管它
here in the Television Centre in London.
为了让电视颜色精确而不过于花哨
To demonstrate colour on television could be both accurate and not garish,
我委办了一个艺术史的系列节目
I commissioned a series about the history of art.
节目名称叫做 文明
It was called Civilisation.
我正站在西斯廷教堂里
I'm standing in the Sistine Chapel
在我上方的就是人类最伟大的杰作之一
and above my head is one of the greatest works of man,
米开朗基罗的天花板
Michelangelo's ceiling.
节目由肯尼斯·克拉克推出后大获成功
It was presented by Kenneth Clarke and became a great success.
所以我们在之后几个节目系列中以相似的手法
So we followed it with other series on a similar scale about science,
阐释了科学 经济和美国史
economics and the history of America.
但我知道野生动物会是最夺目的系列
But I knew the most dazzlingly colourful series would be one about wildlife.
经过八年的管理工作后
After eight years in administration,
我决定要回归制片
I decided I wanted to go back to making programs.
我提议制做13集各60分钟时长的
And I put up a suggestion we should make 13 one-hour programmes
关于追溯地球生命的全部历史的彩色电视节目
in colour tracing the whole history of life on Earth.
地球生命
多亏了喷气式飞机旅行的发展
Thanks to the development of jet air travel,
我们才能在全球三十个国家进行摄影
we were able to film in 30 countries around the globe.
当我追溯地球的生命史之时
And as I traced the history of life on the planet,
我仅通过简单的切换镜头
I could appear to move from one continent to another
就能在各个大陆上现身
in the space of a single sequence.
南美雨林是世界上
The South American rainforests are the richest
最丰富最繁多种类的生命的聚居地
and varied assemblage of life in the world.
摩洛哥的石灰岩
These limestones in Morocco...
生活在日本各地的猕猴
Macaques live in many parts of Japan.
《地球上的生命》在上百个国家公映
Life On Earth was shown in 100 different countries
可能有五亿观众
and seen by perhaps as many as 500 million people.
现在  拍摄自然纪录片电视节目是全球趋势
Natural history television was now a global phenomenon,
它将神奇的世界以彩色形式展现给大众
revealing our wonderful world in colour to all.
在这个系列节目中 我们充分利用彩色和潜水装备
During the series, we made full use of both colour and scuba gear
拍摄到了前人未及的水下世界
to help show the underwater world as never before.
我甚至试过跟着汉斯·哈斯的指导
I even tried to follow Hans Hass' lead
来探索水下世界
exploring the underwater world.
水下摄制的问题之一是
One of the problems with underwater films was
我们不能在水下说话
you cannot talk underwater.
大多数时间里你身上背着呼吸装置
Most of the time if you have a breathing apparatus on your back,
同时嘴里也会塞着点东西
you have something in your mouth.
但是我的同事 阿利斯泰尔 非常敏锐的指出
But Alistair, one of my producer colleagues, was very keen we should
我们该试着 让解说员在水下对着镜头说话
try and introduce the presenter talking to camera underwater.
当时有个绝妙发明 泡泡头盔  就是这个装置
There was a wonderful new invention called the bubble helmet and this is it.
你能在它的一侧放个麦克风
You can put a microphone in one side of it.
所以我们潜入到下榻的宾馆的泳池里
So, we went down to the swimming pool in the hotel where we were staying
这玩意锁紧在我头上
and this was screwed on my head.
锁紧这头盔 用以防水 耗了不少时间
It took a long time to screw it down tight to make it watertight.
我像这样戴上了它
I put it on like this.
我涉水而下 入水还不足一英尺
I waded it into the water and I hadn't gone more than a foot underwater,
突然水开始涌入头盔 情况危急
When suddenly, water started bubbling in, very alarming.
水在你的四周迅速上升 我快要溺亡了
It was rising around you and I was going to drown.
要多久才能把这玩意搞下来
How long would it take to get this off?
所以我急忙出水 说 这上面有条裂缝
So I came out in a hurry. There was a fault, I said.
阿利斯泰尔说 这不可能 我试试 并把头盔戴上
"Nonsense," said Alistair, "give it to me." He put it on his shoulders.
而我甚至有点幸灾乐祸地 把头盔锁的相当紧
And I, with some pleasure screwed it down quite tight
他也下了泳池
and he waded into the pool.
而且比我更快的带着水钻了出来
And he came out even quicker than me with water
手忙脚乱地要把头盔摘下来
and he was gesticulating to get it off.
我好不容易把头盔摘下来后
And I finally took it off
他说 的确有裂缝
and he said, "There's a fault."
我说 是的 确实有
I said, "Yes, there is".
所以我快乐地把头盔扔了
So I happily left the helmet behind
用回我的旧面具和水肺
and reverted to my old mask
来进行我下一轮的水下作业-
and scuba gear when it came to my next underwater assignment -
揭示海豚那不同寻常的社会行为和智力
to reveal the extraordinary social behaviour and intelligence of dolphins.
它们充满好奇心
They are full of curiosity,
它们玩耍一切能找到的怪玩意 比如小枝条
they play with odd things they find, such as twigs,
和它们一起游泳的话
and swimming among them leaves you in no doubt
你丝毫不会怀疑它们拥有极高智商
that they are highly intelligent.
它们甚至会模仿
They will even mimic you
你在水中转动或停止的动作
as you spin or hang in the water.
直到1980年代 一次水下摄制最多拍十分钟
Until the 1980s, you could only shoot 10 minutes of film under water
然后你就必须返回水面
before you had to come back to the surface,
打开水下装置 拿出相机
open the underwater housing, take out the camera,
换一卷新胶卷
put in a new roll of film.
不过后来 摄像机解决了这个难题
But then video cameras solved that problem.
录象带能够持续工作三十分钟
Videotapes ran for 30 minutes.
现在我们终于有机会
And now, at last, we had the chance
能够记录水下动物的行为
of properly recording animal behaviour underwater.
另外 摄像机更为灵敏
In addition, video cameras were far more sensitive,
这样我们就能在较低亮度下完成拍摄
so we could record at much lower light levels,
摆脱了对人工照明的依赖
making artificial lights unnecessary.
这对水下拍摄来说是巨大的突破
It was a huge breakthrough for underwater filming,
更是蓝色星球系列节目拍摄成功至关重要的一点
and crucial to the success of The Blue Planet series.
现在 能够第一次记录马林鱼捕食
Now it was possible to record for the first time marlin hunting.
大海大洋里充满了动物
The seas and oceans were full of animals
它们的非常规行为 至今无人目睹过
whose extraordinary behaviour, up till now, no one had ever seen.
拍摄的镜头变得越来越好
And the shots just got better and better.
摄像师可以在水下做足够长时间的逗留
Cameramen could now stay underwater long enough
以便捕捉到每个动作的每个细节
to capture every moment of the action,
并且在正确的时间 正确的地点
and be in the right place at the right time
拍摄最有戏剧性的事件
for the most dramatic events.
所以现在我们能拍到前人未睹的
So now we can capture previously unseen animal behaviour
世界各处海洋生物的行为
throughout the seas of the world.
而时至今日 在陆地上 我们还不能在
On land it had, until now, been impossible to film animals
多数哺乳动物活跃的夜间拍摄动物行为
behaving naturally at night, when most mammals are active.
我们能做的就是打个光点在它们身上
All we could do was shine a spotlight on them
它们一边逃 我们一边追着拍
and film them as they ran away.
对在黑暗中生活的动物 问题同样如此
And it was the same problem wherever animals lived in darkness.
洞穴是极其引人入胜的地方 却难以在里面拍摄
Caves are fascinating places, but difficult places to work in.
回想1972年我第一次来到婆罗洲的哥曼东洞穴时
When I first came here to this one in Gomantong in Borneo back in 1972,
我们不得不带上大量光源设备
we had to bring a lot of lights with us
以此拍摄居住其中的数百万的
in order to film the many millions of birds and bats
鸟类和蝙蝠
that live in here.
而且那些生物的粪便
And the droppings of all those creatures
使洞穴充斥着氨气
make the cave wreak of ammonia.
这股味道让我一下子回想起来
The smell brings it all back to me.
40年前我来这的时候
When I was here 40 years ago,
导演说 在这洞穴的最深处
the director said, "There's a pile of droppings
有一大坨屎
at the far end of the cave
直堆到洞顶
that goes right up to the roof."
你干嘛不爬到最顶上去
"Why don't you climb up to the top?"
然后我到了顶上 他大吼说 说句话
And when I got to the top he shouted, "Say something!"
所以我试了一下
So I tried.
然后 发生的是
And...what it is is...
那些在洞顶上成群而聚的蝙蝠
these bats... packed tight on the roof here.
就在我头边乱飞
They're flying now all around my head.
这个洞 这个最特别的部分
This cave, this particular part of it,
哦 使得
Oohh! ..makes...
氨气真的让人相当窒息
This ammonia is really quite, quite choking.
使得这个地方变成一个完美的家
..makes a very perfect place for a home.
让人惊讶的是 这里极多数量的
One of the really astounding things is that this immense number of bats
惊慌乱飞的蝙蝠
flying round here in a panic -
却没有一只和其他的撞车
not one is colliding with the other.
我也的确没有处在被它们撞到的危险之中
Nor, indeed, am I in any danger whatsoever of being hit by them.
然后导演说 卡  摄像停止
And then the director said, "Cut!", the camera stopped,
光源灭掉
the lights went out,
而后一只蝙蝠直撞在我脸上
and a bat flew straight in my face.
所以它们享受盛赞的声波定位
So perhaps their much praised echo location
可能并不如人们所说的那么完美
is not quite as perfect as people say.
那时我们用的相机需要像这样的普通的白光
The film cameras we used then needed normal white light, like these.
但是这样带来的问题是 光会干扰
But the problem with that
那些惯于生活在黑暗中的动物
is that they disturb animals accustomed to living in the dark.
但随后安全行业研发出一种新型摄像机
But then the security industry developed a new type of camera
像这个一样  用红外光 不需要这种光源
like this one, which uses infrared light and doesn't need these lights,
但是黑暗中依然在能够看得见
but nonetheless can see in the dark, as you can see -
我关掉这一个 我关掉另一个
I turn off one, I turn off the other...
现在就算是彻底的黑暗 你也能看见我
..and now, even though it's pitch dark, you can see me.
大多数动物 跟我们一样看不见红外光
Most animals, like us, can't see infrared.
所以使用这种相机就意味着
And that meant that with these cameras,
我们能看见动物在黑暗中完全自然的行为
we could now watch them behave perfectly normally in the dark.
这揭示了一些不同寻常的行为
And that revealed some extraordinary behaviour.
也引起了一两件让人不太舒服的事
And also led to one or two pretty uncomfortable moments.
狮子在夜里是相当活跃的
Lions are mostly active at night,
在白天它们甚少吼叫
and seldom roar during the day.
在科学家的帮助下  通过对着当地的头狮播放陌生狮子的吼声
We tried to persuade them to do so with the help of scientists,
我们尝试诱使它们吼叫
by playing back the roar of a strange lion to a resident pride.
丝毫不起作用
Even that didn't work.
12年后 我开着一部侧开门的路虎
But 12 years later, I set off in an open-sided Land Rover with
带上最新的红外线技术设备 准备再试一次
the latest infrared technology to try again.
和往常一样它们都在睡觉
As usual, they were sleeping.
我得等到夜幕降临
I would have to wait for darkness.
我们启动了车
We drive up.
我在一侧开 相机在另一侧
I go on one side, the camera goes on the other.
狮子开始吼叫
And the lion starts roaring.
但是问题是我看不见它在哪
But the problem is, I can't see where it is.
我甚至都看不到相机在哪
I can't even see where the camera is.
制片人说 开始
"Cue", says the producer.
我就开始说我的台词
So I start trying to say my piece.
并试着表现的没有被
Trying not to be too frightened of this lion
就藏身在黑暗中的某处 感觉最多离我就几码远  路虎旁边
which is somewhere in the blackness, and, as far as I can make out,
的狮子过度吓到
within a couple of yards of me and no side on the Land Rover.
不清楚相机位置的情况下
And I then had to do my piece to camera looking around,
我四处张望 还要对着它说台词
seeing where on earth the camera was.
现在 黑夜之中 在我附近
And now in the darkness there are a number of them roaring...
有好几头狮子都在吼叫
just around here.
我知道在我三四码范围之内 有两只
There are two, I know, within three or four yards of where I am,
在那边20码开外 有第三只
and a third, perhaps 20 yards over there.
那时一片漆黑 所以我并不太确定
Though it's difficult to tell because it's pitch black.
那不是有攻击性的吼声 是交流的信号
Those are not aggressive roars, they are communication roars,
但是在夜幕之下
but they are quite enough to chill the blood
它们也足够让人胆战心惊
in the blackness of the night.
几年后 将整个红外线光源的电池放在车顶上
A few years later, similar technology made it possible to film
这项类似的技术 使得我们能够
one of the most extraordinary hunting sequences ever recorded,
拍摄到史上最不同寻常的捕猎镜头
using whole batteries of infrared lights mounted on vehicles.
单只狮子是没有任何机会成功的
A solitary lion stands no chance,
但是整个狮群都在这
but the whole pride is here.
有30只
There are 30 of them,
猎杀大象是它们的专长
and they are specialist elephant hunters.
这绝妙的行为以前未曾以其他方式摄制下来
This remarkable behaviour could not have been filmed in any other way,
它也确切的证实了很多人的疑问
and it proved conclusively what many others had doubted -
一大群狮子的确可以
that a big pride of lions can indeed bring down and kill
猎杀如大象那样大体型的动物
an animal as big as an elephant.
另一种相机仅仅是利用
Other cameras were developed that worked simply by concentrating
聚集微弱星光和月光来工作
what little light comes from the stars and moon.
我们用这种星光相机记录了
And we used such a starlight camera to record an encounter I had
我遇到过的一种 神奇的新西兰昼伏夜出的鸟
with a wonderful New Zealand nocturnal bird,
几维鸟
the kiwi.
我们打听到了几维鸟从灌木丛出来
We heard of a place where kiwis came out of the bush
并沿着海岸漫步
and walked along the beach
寻找沙蚤的地点
looking for sandhoppers.
它们通过嗅觉来认路
Now they find their way by smell,
所以我就想 我怎么隐藏自己
so I thought, how can I conceal myself?
所以我躺在有大量腐烂的海藻的海岸线上
So I lay on the tideline where all the rotting seaweed was lying.
我就在那躺着
And I just lay on it.
一会 这种迷人的小生物就慢慢的靠了过来
And this little...enchanting little creature came slowly along,
它把喙插入沙里探察
probing its beak into the sand.
咻 的吹开沙子 再深入些 咻
Phwff! Blowing out the sand. Coming closer. Phwff!
用鼻孔探沙这招效果很不错
'Probing sand with your nostrils is all very well,
但是沙子的确会堵住鼻孔
'but it does clog them up.
所以每次吹沙必须吹的十分干净
'So you need to blow them clear every now and then.'
几维鸟的嗅觉极其敏锐
'It's sense of smell is so acute,
无需看到  它们就能
'it can pick out the largest juiciest hoppers
从沙子深处揪出最大最多汁的沙蚤
deep in the sand 'without even seeing them.'
星光相机远比我看的清楚
Our starlight camera can see much better than I can.
我需要一个电筒来看清楚这种奇妙的动物
'I need a torch to see this extraordinary creature properly.
但是它似乎不介意
'But he doesn't seem to mind.'
因为眼睛很小  它径直走到我面前
He comes right up to me because his eyes are very small.
糟糕的视力令它极其温顺
Poor eyesight is putting it mildly.
因为海藻腐烂的味道遮住了我的体味
But he can smell, but he didn't.
它本可以闻到我 但实际却没有
Because the seaweed was even stronger smelling than me.
在夜间还有其他的拍摄方式
There are other ways of filming in the dark -
就是使用像这样的热成像摄像机
by using thermal cameras like this one.
我头的上方 有很多蝙蝠
Up above me there are a lot of bats.
相机能以不同的颜色来显示它们
And the camera shows them as different colours.
黄色显示的是刚刚飞进山洞的蝙蝠
The yellow lights here are bats that have just flown in
因为飞行刚结束而它们的身体仍在发热
and are still warm from their exertion.
除了能够显示动物的所在位置
as well as revealing where animals are,
热成像摄像机还能显示其他东西
the thermal cameras can also reveal something of the condition they are in.
例如，因为我有体温
For example, my face now, because I'm rather hot,
此刻 我的脸可能显示的是橙色
is likely to be an orange colour.
我体温相对低的部位就会显示红色
Where I am cooler it will be red,
就像这里 应该是蓝色的
and this probably, is verging on blue.
但如果我拿一瓶冷水 它就可能是黑色的
But if I take a bottle of cold water, that's likely to be black.
啊~~~  很好喝
Ahhh! Very good, too.
在加拉帕戈斯群岛 热成像摄像机也能派上用场
Thermal cameras also proved useful in the Galapagos,
它能显示出爬行动物
to demonstrate some
一些较显著的生理适应特性
of the remarkable physiological adaptations of reptiles.
一旦它们暖身完毕
Once they are thoroughly warmed up,
海洋鬣蜥就能像我的一样
marine iguanas can maintain their body temperature
保持体温
just about as constantly as I can.
更重要的是 它们体温和我的大致相同
And what's more, at about the same level,
事实上它们的体温可能会稍高些 大约37°C
or indeed, slightly higher - around 37 degrees centigrade.
但当它们进入到冰冷的海洋里 进食海藻时
But when they go into the cold sea to feed on submerged seaweed,
其体温会下降的非常迅速
their temperature falls very rapidly.
刚出水的那只绿鬣蜥是黑色的 它全身寒澈
A recently emerged iguana is black. It's chilled to the bone.
现在它们需要热能 以便消化吃掉的海藻
Now they need heat in order to be able to digest that meal of seaweed,
现在 它们通过在这些阳光照耀着的热黑岩石上
and they get that by spread-eagling themselves
伸展四肢来获取热量
on these black, hot, sun-baked rocks.
所以 热成像摄像机刚刚拍摄到了
So, thermal cameras reveal just how skilled
爬行动物在如何熟练的利用太阳能
reptiles are at harnessing the power of the sun.
在刚开始拍摄《生命之源》的时候
One of the things we discovered when starting work
我们发现了一点
on the Trials of Life
相机在其近处有物体
was a new lens which enabled you to have an object close to the camera -
也许是非常微小的生物   的情况下
a small little creature, perhaps -
仍然要具有任意距离变焦的清晰镜头
and yet have all the distance to the far horizon in complete focus.
所以我需要具备保证
So I would be able to walk up from the distance to something close to camera,
从远处走到相机近处一直有清晰镜头的能力
all the time being in focus.
确定相互依赖的团队关系
It's not always easy to decide in these partnerships,
并不容易
which is exploiting which.
优势平衡往往非常微妙
The balance of advantage is often very delicate.
举个例子，这些位于澳大利亚的蚂蚁
Take for example these ants in Australia.
非常凶猛
They are extremely ferocious,
通常它们会
and normally they will
撕裂毛毛虫的身体
rip apart any caterpillar.
看 它们是怎样对付这只的
But see how they're treating this one.
当我们第一次在戏剧院里看到此情景的时候
When we first saw that shot in the viewing theatre...
所有人去了餐厅边喝茶边讨论
We all went down to the canteen for a cup of tea and talked about it,
我听到在我的身后
and I heard someone next to me,
一个刚刚加入团队的人
who'd just joined the team
在与她的朋友谈话
talking to her friend,
她说  他们在澳大利亚拍到的东西太奇妙了  真叹为观止
and she said, "Fantastic stuff they've got in Australia. Amazing!
但我自己绝不会到那里去
"But I would never want to go there myself,
因为那里有两英尺长的毛毛虫
"because they have caterpillars there that are two feet long!"
所以 有时候光学技巧可以让我们茅塞顿开
So, sometimes with all our optical tricks, we can get too clever.
不过 昆虫的特写镜头相当具有魅力
Never the less, insects filmed in close-up are truly fascinating.
这些是婆罗洲的树蚁
These are tree ants in Borneo,
它们筑巢的方式非常美妙
and they have a wonderful way of making their nests.
早在50年代 当我来到婆罗洲的时候
I first tried to film how they did so,
我第一次拍摄到它们是如何筑巢的
when I was here in Borneo back in the '50s.
我们注意到这一组蚂蚁
'Then we noticed this group
用口器咬紧低处的树叶
'with their jaws locked tight in the lower leaf,
其后腿搭在较高处的叶子
'and their hind legs attached to the upper leaf.
蚁群正在修建新的巢穴
'The colony is constructing a new nest.
这些耐心的工蚁
'And these patient workers
正在保持作为未来巢穴的两片叶子的位置
'are holding two leaves of the future nest in position,
以便其他蚂蚁
'so that other members
可以将之紧固在一起
'can fasten them together
建成它们新巢穴的外墙
'to form the outer wall of their new home.'
为了得到这些镜头 我们必须撕开巢穴
To get those shots, we had to tear apart the nest to get
才能将蚂蚁的工作情况公布于众
the ants to work out in the open.
时至今日  我们能做得更好
These days we can do better than that.
这是个光学探头 我能够控制其前后
This is an optical probe that I can make mover forwards or
甚至左右移动
backwards and even...from side to side.
利用这个工具 你可以去到巢穴里一探究竟
And so with that, you can go into the nest
拍摄到蚂蚁非常自然的行为
and get shots of the ants behaving totally naturally.
这是巢穴里的不速之客
That is a stranger in the nest.
这是它们捕获的小虫
That is a little bug which they are attacking.
类似于这些技术的发展使我们
It was technical developments like these that allowed us
最终能够进入到昆虫的世界
eventually to enter the world of the insect.
机械起重臂能使制片人将摄像机悬挂在
A motorised jib arm enables filmmakers to suspend a camera above
一纵队侵略性工蚁的正上方并观察到它们有序的运输方式
a column of aggressive driver ants and watch the organised way
它们在森林中捕食
they hunt through the forest.
工蚁携带着幼蚁
Workers carry the colony's larvae.
凶猛的士兵们的腿形成一个防御性的墙壁
Ferocious soldiers link legs to form a defensive roof and walls,
有组织地包围着运输队伍
enclosing the column.
如果我们的摄像机或者摄影师不小心碰到他们
Were the camera or cameraman to accidentally touch
哪怕只是一个兵蚁 它们会立即反击
just one of these soldiers, they would all immediately attack.
但它们眼不见物
But they're blind,
所以它们看不到悬挂在它们头顶上方仅数厘米的摄像机
and they can't see the camera hanging just centimetres above them.
因此 我们可以一直跟踪携带猎物的工蚁
So we can track along with them as the army takes its prey
返回到蚁后正在等待的营地
back to the bivouac where the queen is waiting.
制作野生动物电影需耗费极大的耐心
Wildlife film-making can take a lot of patience.
为拍摄某个特定的动作  摄影师可能要花上
Cameramen may have to spend hours and hours,
几个小时 几天 甚至几周的时间
if not days and weeks, to film one particular action.
但现代的安全科技可以协助拍摄上述工作
But that can be helped using modern security technology.
我们使用这种技术拍到了某些
And we used such technology to get a shot of something
据我所知 此前从未拍摄过的录像
that as far as I know, had never been filmed before in the wild.
狩猎的响尾蛇
Rattlesnakes hunting.
在纽约州工作的科学家已经将无线电发射器植入进
Scientists working in New York State had implanted radio transmitters in
一群响尾蛇中 以便能用天线追踪它们
a group of rattlesnakes so that each could be found by using an aerial.
它在那儿
There he is.
摄制组将远程控制摄像机
The camera crew placed remotely controlled cameras
与红外光源设置在准备捕猎的蛇旁边
and infrared lights next to a snake lying in ambush.
摄像机连接到运动传感器上 若是其拍摄范围内有任何东西移动
The cameras were attached to motion detectors that would turn them on
它就会自动启动拍摄
if anything moved in their field of vision.
次日晚上 我查看录像
The following night I checked the replay.
那有一只老鼠
There's a mouse.
这时漆黑一片
It's pitch dark
显然老鼠完全没有意识到蛇的存在
and the mouse clearly has no idea the snake is there.
但是 蛇清楚地察觉到了老鼠
Bu the snake is well aware of the mouse.
它已经计算出老鼠逃跑的路径
He's worked out that that is the path along which the mice run.
哦，我的天啊！
Oh, my goodness!
毫无疑问 这只老鼠死定了
That's a dead mouse, all right.
因家用防盗而产生的技术
So it was that technology designed to keep burglars out of our homes,
使得我们能在野外记录响尾蛇的狩猎方式
enabled us to record the rattlesnake's hunting strategy in the wild.
另一种革命性的拍摄技术能够控制播放的时间
Another revelatory film technique involves playing with time
慢放动画
slowing down the action.
摄像师很早前通过简单地增加每秒拍摄图像的数量
Cameramen have long done that,
来做到这一点
simply by increasing the number of images taken per second.
红隼之所以称为风之子
Kestrels are known as wind-hoverers,
是由于其展现的在空中悬停的能力
because of their apparent ability to hang motionless in the air.
而慢镜头让我们能看到其中
And slow motion photography enables us to see details
用肉眼无法看清楚的飞行细节
of their flying technique that we can't see with the naked eye.
用特殊的相机拍摄这只受过训练的鸟
By filming this trained bird, with this special camera,
我们放慢镜头 观察它们究竟是如何做到的
we can slow down the motion and see exactly how they do it.
它与迎面而来的风以相同的速度飞行
It's flying at the same speed as the oncoming wind
流经它翅膀的空气提供了足够的升力维持其飞行
and the air flowing over its wings  provides just enough lift top keep it airborne.
若像这样慢慢飞行 它们会面临失速的风险
By flying as slowly as this, they risk stalling,
因为经过翅膀的气流无法提供足够的升力
because the wind flow over the wing doesn't provide enough lift.
将动作放慢10倍的时候
Slowing down the action by ten times
我们可以看到红隼伸展翅膀前缘的指状突起
we can see how the kestrel extends  the finger-like projection on the leading edge of its wing
并伸开尾翼以产生更多的升力
and spreads its tail-feathers to generate more lift.
商业客机用同样的方式
Commercial airliners do the same thing
调整襟翼缓慢着陆
when they adjust their wing flaps to slow them down for landing.
如果红隼在盘旋中想成功盯住猎物
If a kestrel is to see its prey successfully while hovering,
就必须保持头部完全静止
it has to keep its head perfectly still,
但在风的持续干扰下 这并不不容易
not easy when the wind is constantly trying to blow you off position.
但在慢镜头回放中
But in slow motion,
你可以看到红隼是如何顺应着风即刻变动的
you can see how the kestrel responds immediately to changes in the wind.
它不断调整翅膀
Constantly adjusting the set of its wings
并使脖子伸缩自如
and allowing it's neck to stretch and contract.
所以即便其身体不断移动
So that while its body is constantly moving,
但它的眼睛保持固定 并能发现地面上微小的活动
its eyes stay fixed and can spot the slightest movement on the ground below.
我最喜欢的慢镜头之一就是
One of my favourite slow-motion moments was
我用射豆枪戏耍处在繁殖期的食蚜蝇
when I was able to fool a lovesick hoverfly with a peashooter.
它似乎是完全静止不动
It might seem that he's absolutely motionless,
但事实上
but, in fact,
他根据气流的轻微变化而在空中做不断调整
he's having to make continual  changes to adjust for slight currents in the air.
这是令人惊叹的飞行特技
It's an amazing piece of acrobatics,
远胜过我们用直升机所能做的一切
far better than anything that we could do in a helicopter.
而它做这一切都是为了向雌性展示
And it's all done in order
它守候领地的超凡能力
to impress the female
以便给其留下深刻的印象
to show her that he is superb at holding his territory.
凭借其超群的视力 它已经准备好发现任何
With his superb eyesight, he's ready to spot anything
从它身边呼啸而过并有可能是雌性蝇的物体
that might whiz by him at high speed that could be a female.
我仅用一把射豆枪就能戏耍它
And I might just be able to fool him with a peashooter.
通过放慢50倍速左右来观察它的反应
By watching his response slowed down by about 50 times,
显而易见 雄性蝇确实是过于兴奋
it's clear that the male is indeed
以至于会追随任在身旁的快速移动的物体
so hyped up that he will pursue any fast-moving object
并希冀将会是雌性蝇
that comes near him in the hope that it might be a female.
等到我测试完成之后
Those poor males must have been exhausted
这些可怜的雄性蝇一定是筋疲力尽了
by the time I'd finished with them.
通过将数码慢动作摄像机
By combining the best macro-lenses
和最棒的微距镜头结合
with digital slow-motion cameras,
我们能够揭示一些更微小的生物的
we were able to reveal the extreme athletic prowess
超凡运动能力
of some even tinier creatures.
就像它们名字所显示的
These springtails, as they're name suggests,
这些跳虫有更为新颖的跳跃方式
have a rather novel way of jumping.
其腹部下方有一个微型双管具弹器
They have a tiny two-pronged lever beneath their abdomen.
轻轻一弹便可使其飞射到空中
One small flick from it can catapult them six inches,
6英寸高 约15厘米
some 15 centimetres, into the air.
这相当于一个人纵身跳过埃菲尔铁塔
It's the equivalent of a human being jumping over the Eiffel Tower.
因此通过慢镜头摄像机
So with slow-motion cameras,
我们可以看清并区分肉眼无法看到的动作细节
we can watch actions and distinguish details that are impossible to see with the naked eye.
在另一方面来说 我们可以操纵拍摄时间
At the other end of the scale, we can manipulate time
加快极其缓慢的动作
to speed up excessive slow action.
这是一个延时摄影工作室
This is a time-lapse studio
在这里你可以非常精确的控制灯光和相机
where you can control lights and cameras very precisely.
胶片摄像机每秒拍摄25帧
A film camera shoots 25 frames per second,
但如果你修改成每秒拍摄一帧
but if you modify one so that it only shoots one frame per second
然后以正常的速度播放
and then show the film at normal speed,
那么 你就将动作加快了25倍
well, then, you increase the speed of action by 25 times.
随着延时摄影愈发先进
And as the sophistication of time-lapse photography has increased,
我们发现了植物有着
so we've been able to show that plants
和动物一样的竞争力和侵略性
can be as competitive and aggressive as many an animal.
延时摄影也帮助我们
And it was the mastery of time-lapse
制作了名为植物私生活的系列节目
that allowed us to make a series called The Private Life of Plants.
将3个月时间浓缩成20秒
Condense three months into 20 seconds,
冬天的苍凉迅速转变成春天的温暖
and the desolation of winter quickly warms into the riot of spring.
将一周时间加快成一分钟
Speed a week into a minute,
你便能体会到这种
and you can sense the urgency
来自于地被植物争先恐后去开花的紧迫感
with which the ground-living plants race to unfurl their flowers.
不起眼的荆棘是最积极生长的森林植物之一
Of all the woodland plants, the humble bramble is one of the most aggressive.
它从一边到另一边摇曳着生机勃勃的嫩芽
It waves its shoots agitatedly from side to side
似乎在探索前行的最佳途径
as if feeling for the best way forward.
藤蔓上的倒棘刺
The invading stem's backward-pointing spines
为其攀爬几乎所有助于它生长的东西
give it the grip it needs to climb almost anything
提供了助力
that stands in its way.
它一天差不多可以生长7厘米
It can advance as much as seven centimetres in a day.
现在 数码相机使我们见证了
Now digital cameras allow us to see
镜头正以何种方式在发展着
how a shot is developing while
而我们还是会用它
we are still taking it,
而不必非要等它完善到
instead of having to wait till it was finished
和曾用过的胶片相机一样水准的时候
as we used to have to do with film cameras.
我们也可以用电脑连接小型马达
And we can also use computers attached to small motors
使摄像机在一定帧数内移动
to move a camera in-between exposed frames,
以便其能与植物同行
so that the camera can, in fact, travel alongside the plant.
应用这种新技术
Using this new technology,
就能将林地春天到来的过程
it became possible to condense the arrival of spring in a woodland
凝结到数秒钟
into a few seconds.
野生动物影片制作中最美妙的事情
But the wonderful thing about wildlife film making
就是无论你见识和拍摄过多少事物
is that no matter how much you've seen and filmed,
总会有一些东西能带给你惊喜
there's always going to be something to surprise you.
我记得早在1994年
I remember back in 1994,
当时我们在拍摄生长在婆罗洲山区
we were filming nepenthes rajah, the largest pitcher plant in the world,
世界上最大的猪笼草 马来王猪笼草
growing up in the mountains of Borneo.
我猜想它是如何获得氮肥的
And I made an assumption about how it obtained its nitrogen fertiliser.
我想这颗…
I guess this one...
包含... 两或三品脱的液体 [约1.1~1.7升]
contains... two or three pints of liquid.
它如此之大以至于不仅能捕食到昆虫
It's so big that it catches not just insects
甚至还有小型啮齿动物
but even small rodents.
并且有老鼠尸体落入其中的记载
And one was recorded that has in it the body of a drowned rat.
所以在植物界若是真有食肉植物
So if ever there was a carnivore among plants,
那就是它了
this is it.
但 我错了
But I was wrong.
2010年 科学家发现了植物是以一种全新方式
In 2010, scientists discovered that the plant gets its nitrogen
获取氮肥
in a quite different way.
我们忍不住回去
And we couldn't resist going back to see
看看是否能发现真相
if we could find out what the truth was.
沙巴州的京那巴鲁山
Mount Kinabalu in Sabah
是众多马来王猪笼草的家园
is home to many rajah pitcher plants.
看起来就像其他类型猪笼草一样
They certainly seem to attract insects
它们确实是为了吸引昆虫落入圆筒形捕虫笼内
that fall into their bowls just as other pitchers do,
但它们也有较大的访客
but they also have larger visitors.
树鼩
A tree shrew.
它在舔舐笼盖的底面
It's licking the underside of the lid
那上面有着猪笼草为吸引猎物而分泌的蜜汁
where the pitcher secretes nectar with which it lures visitors.
但即使它的臀部搭在捕虫笼的边缘
But even though its backside is hanging over the bowl,
似乎也没有任何陷入和溺水的危险
it doesn't seem to be in any danger of falling in and drowning.
这到底是怎么回事
So what's going on?
它留下了线索
It leaves a clue.
一粒粪便
A dropping.
所以猪笼草就是树鼩的马桶
So the pitcher is a tree shrew toilet.
树鼩舔舐猪笼草笼盖内的分泌物以获取营养
The tree shrew feeds by licking the secretions from the pitcher plant's lid
而猪笼草则通过收集它的粪作为肥料
and the pitcher plant gets its fertiliser by collecting the tree shrew's droppings.
野生动物摄影师们总是尝试去拍摄
Wildlife cameramen are always trying to film
一些人类从未目睹过的动物行为
some piece of animal behaviour that no-one has ever see before.
而航拍能帮助他们做到这一点
And aerial photography enable them to do just that.
在早期
In the early days,
我们偶尔会在小型飞机内拍摄自然景色
we occasionally managed to get up in a small plane to get a shot of the landscape.
但飞机强烈的摆动
But the plane vibrated so much
使你无法使用长焦拍摄动物的特写镜头
that you couldn't use long lenses to get close-ups of animals
而若是低空飞行 引擎的轰鸣则会吓跑动物
and if you went low the roar of the engine frightened them.
因此 我们尝试其他的空运方式
So we tried other forms of aerial transport.
气球相对更加安静
Balloons were a little quieter,
但它们只会随风而动
but they took you where the wind blew them,
却无法到你想去的地方
not where you wanted to go.
因而依旧很难获得稳定的拍摄画面
And getting steady shots was still difficult.
直到一种可以奇迹般保持
It wasn't until the invention of a kind of mount
摄像机相对稳定的运载工具的发明
that could hold the camera almost miraculously free of vibration
才使得运载能从高空中拍摄动物
that it was possible to use the long lenses necessary
而它们不会发现你在那儿的
in order to film animals from a height
必要的长焦镜头成为了可能
and they didn't even know you were there.
在地面上追随狩猎的野狗
It's almost impossible to follow a wild dog hunt at ground level
穿越变化莫测的
through the treacherous swamplands
非洲奥卡万戈三角洲沼泽几乎不可能
of the Okavango Delta in Africa.
但《行星地球》系列节目使用了可以
But the Planet Earth series used a helicopter
携带能保持摄像机相
with a new stabilising mount
对静止的新的稳定装置的直升机
that kept the camera vibration-free
这样你就可以在高空中拍摄特写镜头
and you could get close-ups from so high up
而下方动物则意识不到你在那儿
that the animals below didn't know you were there.
它们去那里了 它们在比赛 它们在比赛
There they go. They're racing. They're racing.
四条狗全部分散开来
Four dogs all spread out.
尽可能跟紧点
Tighten up as much as you can.
通过交切镜头辅以从地面上的拍摄
By inter-cutting aerial shots and shots from the ground,
我们能展示出狗群是如何团队协作
we could show how the dogs worked as a team,
帮助无经验的同伴加入狩猎中
with fresh animals joining the hunt
去攻击它们的猎物并切断其后路
to harry their prey and cut off its escape.
这种全新的镜头为我们提供了巨幅画面
This new perspective gives us the big picture,
帮助我们理解了之前
helping us to understand behaviour
只能看到零星片段的行为
we could only see fragments of before.
跟紧它  它几乎要抓到羚羊了
Stay with him. He's almost got him!
它们正朝水区行进
They're heading towards the water.
喔 鳄鱼会吃掉黑斑羚的
Ooh! The croc's gonna get the impala.
现在我们所拥有的科技可以拍摄
So now we have the techniques to film almost anything
在陆地或海洋或天空上任何的东西
on land or in the sea or in the air.
但想得到已灭绝的动物的图片
But to get pictures of animals that lived in the past,
你不得不再现它们
you have to recreate life.
早期 我们的尝试显得相当粗糙
In the early days, our attempts were pretty crude.
我们把已灭绝的鱼的实体模型放在沼泽上
We used solid models of extinct fish placed in swamps
来说明两栖动物登陆的过程
to show the arrival of amphibians on land.
后来我们绘制恐龙的素描图
We moved on to line drawings of dinosaurs
甚至在我身边出现了一只
and I even appeared alongside one.
很容易想象一些长达12英尺
It's easy to imagine some 12 foot species
如异齿龙这样的洋蜥鳄物种
of pelagosaurus like Dimetrodon
趴在岩石上沐浴着清晨的阳光
lying basking on the rocks in the early morning sun.
然后 我们开始赋予绘画以生命
And then we began to animate the drawings,
但却并不生动
but not very realistically.
需要电脑动画才能使它们
It would take the advent of computer animation
像真正的动物一样活动
to make them move like real animals.
我们希望利用这些新的计算机技术去重现
We wanted to use these new computer techniques to bring to life a moa,
恐鸟这种在新西兰已灭绝的类似鸵鸟的
the giant, extinct ostrich-like bird
巨兽的生活
on New Zealand.
首先 我得要走进林间的空地
First of all, I had to walk into a woodland glade
手握恐鸟骨头
holding a moa bone.
接着将会发生的是
Then what would happen would be that
我放开手 骨头将会悬浮在那儿
that bone would be suspended, I would take my hands away,
而骨架的其余部分将会无端冒出来
and all the rest of the bones and the skeleton would appear from nowhere
以形成完整的骨架
and materialise to form the complete skeleton.
因此 我不得不走进去 拿着骨头
So I had to walk in, hold the bone,
然后放手 让它掉落 这样做看起来很幼稚
then take my hands away and let it drop, which seemed a silly thing to do.
但电子图像合成技术能使它停留在那里
But electronic trickery made it stay there
然后添加恐鸟骨骼的其余部分
and then added the rest of the bones of the moa 's skeleton.
它只有三个脚趾
It had just three toes.
它的骨盆和脊柱使得它的脖子相当长
Its pelvis and its spine lead up to an extraordinarily long neck.
这只鸟站起来超过六英尺 近两米高
This bird stood over six feet, two metres tall.
但后来 我们希望它能走动
But then we wanted it to walk away.
电脑专家让我们去想象它将站在哪
And so what the computer expert got us to do was to imagine where it was going to stand
然后我们藏身在植被里
and then conceal ourselves in the vegetation,
每个人都拿着若干根连接着树枝的鱼线
each of us holding a bit of fishing line attached to a branch.
尽管我们的电脑专家以前是乐队指挥
And with our computer expert conducting us
在他的指导下
as though he was conducting an orchestra,
恐鸟走了进来 拨开树枝
the moa came in, this branch was brushed away,
并伸头去啄动了另一片叶子
and then it reached up and pecked another leaf and the leaf moved
然后它离开了 灌木丛也随之摇摆
and then it moved away and the bushes moved.
这真的很逼真
It was really quite convincing.
第一批在这些岛屿上定居的人类
The first human settlers on these islands
把这些曾看到过的巨兽称之为恐鸟
saw these giants alive and called them moas.
曾经真实存在于世的最高大的恐鸟
Among them were the tallest birds that ever existed,
重达200千克 近400磅
that weighed over 200 kilos, 400 pounds.
所以 现在我们可以随心所欲的重现
So now we could recreate extinct creatures
已经灭绝的生物
whenever we liked,
赋予它们色彩和盎然的生机
in their entire full-colour, animated glory.
一系列科技的不断进步
A succession of technological advances
改变了我们拍摄自然历史影片的方式
has certainly changed the way we make natural history films.
如今 随着时间的推移
These days, with every year that passes,
我们拥有了越来越多的设备
we seem to get more and more equipment.
更长焦的镜头 更多配套的电子设备
Longer lenses, more electronic bits of kit.
但到最后 往往最难忘的镜头却
But in the end, often the most memorable shot comes
来自于对自然界有着深刻的理解的
from just one camera and one person
单机单人
with a deep understanding of the natural world.
拍摄野生雪豹
To film a wild snow leopard
对于野生动物摄影师来说曾是一个终极挑战
was once the ultimate challenge for a wildlife cameraman.
道格 艾伦去喜马拉雅山
Doug Allen went to the Himalayas
尝试完成无数摄影前辈
to attempt to do what so many cameramen before him
未能成功的事
had tried but failed.
我想这里才算是真正的开始
I guess this is where you could say it really starts.
我们正处在雪豹的王国里
We're up here in snow leopard country.
环顾四周 在任何时间 任何地点
You look around and anywhere and at any time,
你都有可能看到它
you might just see it.
山峰恢弘雄伟
These are big, big mountains
却并没有多少雪豹在其中
and there are not many snow leopards.
然而 道格继续躲藏并等待着
Nevertheless, Doug took to his hide and waited.
这太乏味了
This is tedious stuff.
什么都看不到
Not a sign.
现在我若是能得到一丁点的线索
If you got just a little bit of a hint, a wee bit
能目睹一丁点迹象
of a sighting now and again,
都会兴高采烈
your spirits would be lifted.
但现在 我宁愿这种动物少一点魅力
But right now, I'd swap a little bit of this animal's charisma
也想多增加一些可以看见它的可能
for a little bit more visibility.
即使两周过后 事情仍未有任何进展
And things didn't improve, even after two weeks.
是的 当然 这十分无聊
Yeah, of course, it's boring.
这真是无聊得要命
It's as boring as hell.
经过7周耐心的等待和观察
After seven weeks of patiently sitting and watching
这些长焦镜头摄像机都是道格负责拍摄的
these distant shots are all Doug managed to film.
于是 他只能回家  一无所获
So he had to return home empty-handed.
这年冬天 摄影师马克 史密斯
The following winter cameraman Mark Smith
接受了这个挑战
took up the challenge
并且去了另外的地方进行尝试
and tried a different location
这次是在巴基斯坦
this time in Pakistan.
我们刚迎来了一场大雪
We've just got a lot of snow
这样我们就能够追踪到雪豹
and we'll be able to track snow leopard.
因此 我们将有更多机会拍摄到它
So we'll have a lot better chances of filming it.
太棒了
It's just fantastic.
在良好开端之后
After that promising start,
事情未能如马克所愿进展顺利
things didn't go so well for Mark.
他和团队在雪地中跋涉一个月但却无果而归
He and the crew spent a fruitless month trudging through the snow.
整个圣诞节期间 马克都待在山中
Mark spent all Christmas in the mountains
却仍未发现任何雪豹的迹象
with no sign of a snow leopard.
不过 这却是一个无比快乐的新年
But it was a much happier New Year.
刚才…我们刚才得到报告称
Just... We just got a report that
有一只雪豹在山脊上
there's a snow leopard up on the ridge.
而之前我们所处的位置太低
And we were too low where we were before,
所以我们想爬到一定的高度
so we're just trying to get some height
以获得更好的视野
to get a better view of it.
最终 马克有幸首次瞥见了雪豹
Finally, Mark was rewarded with his first ever glimpse.
我抬起头望向山脊
I looked up onto the ridge
我早已看过数以万次
and I could see this leopard-shaped rock,
这种豹形的岩石
which I'd seen a million times before.
我通过望远镜看到一只豹子蹲坐在那里
And I looked through binoculars and it was a leopard just sat there.
它只是位于一块岩石的顶端
It was perched just on the top of a rock
低头看着我们并摆出类似于
and it looked down at us and sat down
狮身人面像般的姿势蹲坐了下来
in a sort of sphinx-like posture.
若干天之后 马克的耐心有了回报
A few days later, Mark's patience paid off.
他不仅发现了一只成年雌性
There was not jut an adult female,
还有它一岁大的幼仔
but with her a one-year-old cub.
马克总共在巴基斯坦花费了8个月的时间
Overall, Mark spent eight months in Pakistan.
勇于献身的精神
And his dedication enabled him to document
使他能够记录下雪豹生活中
the most intimate moments
包括捕猎在内的
of a snow leopard's life.
最为亲密的时刻
Including a hunt.
她静静守在猎物位置上方
Silently she positions herself above her prey.
时至今日 野生动物影片所带来的启示
The revelations brought by wildlife films today
远远超出了60年前我刚起步之时的设想
were beyond my imagination when I set out 60 years ago.
它们不仅改变了我们对大自然的认知
They have transformed not only our understanding of the natural world,
而且还改变了我们对它的态度
but our attitudes towards it.
在过去的五六十年间里
There have been a lot of changes
我们拍摄大自然的方式
in the way that we've filmed the natural world
已经有了翻天覆地的变化
during the last 50-60 years,
但与此同时
but there's also been
我们对世界的认知也发生了极大的改变
a great change in the way we understand that world
那将会是在下一个节目中我所着眼的部分
and that's what I'll be looking at in the next programme.